So that's our offer. We think it's a fair
one, with advantages for both sides.
Yes, well, we're prepared to consider your
offer Ms Chan, if you can accept some conditions.
And subject to consideration by the board.
What are the conditions?
Well, firstly the price you're proposing.
Would that be variable depending on currency
fluctuations? The issue is that we're in an
unstable environment at the moment - the exchange
rate could affect us negatively.
Us too!
True, but the problem is that we're tied to
the U.S. dollar.
We could consider hedging against currency
in both directions.
That would be acceptable.
Another problem we may have is that of supply.
Our customers often need supply at short notice.
If we do get large orders, we need to guarantee
delivery, so we need to stockpile. The difficulty
there is the capital outlay. How would you
feel about a partial offset against our sales?
You mean a loan.
I suppose so.
Would you be agreeable to a deferred payment?
We can provide security of course.
I think that would be acceptable. Unfortunately,
I would need to get Board approval for it.
Of course.
Then I think we might have a deal!
In principle.
Time to celebrate!
In negotiations, it's usual for each side
to have conditions that make the deal better,
or safer for them. A condition is a change
in the terms of a deal which is necessary
before one side or the other agrees.
Yes, well, we're prepared to consider your
offer Ms Chan, if you can accept some conditions.
Notice that Victor uses language carefully.
He doesn't say "we agree to your offer", he
says "we're prepared to consider your offer".
He is signalling to the other side that there
is a chance for agreement by using the word
consider, which means think about .
He then makes this conditional by saying,
if you can accept some conditions. In English,
using the word 'if' in this way is called
a conditional.
Victor is saying, "We can consider your offer
if you can accept some conditions." One part
of the sentence is conditional on, or depending
on the other.
The negative is also true. If they can't accept
the conditions, Victor can't consider the
offer.
Notice that Sue adds: subject to consideration
by the board. 'Subject to' is another type
of conditional phrase. She means, "We can
agree if the board agrees."
'Subject to' is a legal phrase meaning 'only
if', or 'only after'. There are a number of
expressions you can use when giving a condition.
Try them after me:
subject to the board's agreement.
conditional on the board's agreement.
providing that the board agrees.
as long as the board agrees.
on condition that the board agrees.
Let's look now at Victor's first condition.
Firstly the price you're proposing. Would
that be variable depending on currency fluctuations?
The issue is that we're in an unstable environment
at the moment - the exchange rate could affect
us negatively.
When Victor is talking about conditions - he
is exploring various scenarios - or things
that could happen.
Notice that he explains what the problem is.
He says, "The issue is that we're in an unstable
environment."
'The issue' means the problem, or the thing
that needs discussing.
Practise with Victor some ways of introducing
a problem.
The issue is the exchange rate.
The problem is the exchange rate.
The difficulty we have is with the exchange
rate.
One thing that could happen is that the exchange
rate, the amount of money you can exchange
in one currency for another, may change. Notice
that Victor uses the words 'would' and 'could'.
'Would' is like a conditional. One thing might
result in another thing happening.
The exchange rate might change.
Victor is talking about the price for their
product. He asks, "Would that be variable
depending on currency fluctuations?"'Fluctuations
are changes. We can express this another way:
If the currency changes, will the price change?
'Could' is used to express a possibility - something
that might happen.
Victor says, "the exchange rate could affect
us negatively". Notice that you can say something
will affect you negatively - it will have
a negative, or bad effect, or positively - it
will have a positive, or good effect.
What is Lin's response to this first condition,
or concern of Victor's?
We could consider hedging against currency
in both directions.
That would be acceptable.
Like Victor, Lin is being careful. She uses
the word 'consider' rather than just agreeing.
She's waiting until the whole deal is clear.
We can give both questions and answers using
these 'could' and 'would' phrases. Practise
them after Lin and Victor.
Would you consider hedging against currency?
Would you agree to hedging against currency?
We could consider hedging against currency.
We could agree to hedging against currency.
Sue comments: That would be acceptable. 'Acceptable'
simply means able to be accepted. They can
agree to this solution. Practise with Sue
some phrases you can use to agree, and disagree,
to conditions.
That would be acceptable.
We can agree to that.
We would be agreeable to that.
That wouldn't be acceptable I'm afraid.
I'm afraid we can't agree to that.
We wouldn't be agreeable to that.
Notice that to 'agree with' someone, is to
think they are right. To 'agree to' something,
is to accept a proposal.
What is Victor's second condition? Let's see.
If we do get large orders, we need to guarantee
delivery - so we need to stockpile. The difficulty
there is the capital outlay. How would you
feel about a partial offset against our sales?
You might use the phrase 'how would you feel
about' something if you think it may be a
difficult condition for the other side to
accept. Sue puts this proposal a different
way.
Would you be agreeable to a deferred payment?
We can provide security of course.
I think that would be acceptable. Unfortunately,
I would need to get Board approval for it.
Sue uses the phrase would you be agreeable
: Would you be agreeable to a deferred payment?
A deferred payment is when you pay later for
something you buy. Lin thinks this condition
is acceptable, but she makes it conditional
on Board approval by saying, "I would need
to get Board approval." Notice the stress
on would . Practise some phrases you can use
for this type of condition.
That would have to have Board approval.
The Board would need to approve that.
That would be subject to Board approval.
Sometimes conditions depend on other conditions.
One side might say, "We agree to your condition
if"
So it's very important when negotiating to
listen for words that signal a condition:
words like if, could, would,
provided or providing,
as long as and subject to.
And words that might signal a problem, such
as
problem, unfortunately, and however .
Notice that even at the end, they are being
careful about what they say.
Then I think we might have a deal!
In principle.
Lin agrees in principle. This means they have
agreed on terms among themselves, but as she
needs Board approval, she can't authorise
the agreement right now.
And right now we've reached the end of today's
program. See you next time on the Business
of English.